<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grimalkin, or, The Rebel-cat a novel representing the unwearied attempts of the beasts of his faction against sovereignty and succession since the death of the lyons in the tower.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11294981</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11294981</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47322</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47322)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1462:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Grimalkin, or, The Rebel-cat a novel representing the unwearied attempts of the beasts of his faction against sovereignty and succession since the death of the lyons in the tower.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A satire on the intrigues of the Earl of Shaftesbury and the Duke of Monmouth to alter the succession"--British Museum Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Anecdotes</term>
               <term>Monmouth, James Scott, --  Duke of, 1649-1685 --  Anecdotes</term>
               <term>Monmouth's Rebellion, 1685 --  Anecdotes</term>
               <term>Political satire, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47322:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GRIMALKIN, OR, THE REBEL-CAT: A NOVELL Repreſenting the Unwearied Attempts of the Beaſts of his Faction Againſt SOVEREIGNTY and SUCCESSION Since the Death of the LYONS in the TOWER.</p>
            <q>Dic mihi, ſi fias tu <hi>Leo,</hi> qualis eris?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="novel">
            <pb facs="tcp:47322:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47322:2"/>
            <head>GRIMALKIN, OR The Rebell-CAT: A NOVELL: Repreſenting the Unwearied Attempts of the Beaſts of his Faction againſt SOVEREIGNTY and SUCCESSION, ſince the Death of the <hi>Lyons</hi> in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU cannot but have heard of the late Havock and Depopulations which Death hath made in the Tower among the Lyons. No leſs than Three of the Royal Line being Dead at once: And what is obſerved by ſome, to the great Grief and Aſtoniſhment of all, that the Deceaſed Lyons (of happy memory) were Proteſtant Lyons, and their Succeſſor, who onely now ſurvives, a Popiſh Lyon. But ſuch as are not without Hopes of the Eſtabliſhment of what they call Proteſtant Religion, with, or without the Government, talk of his being remov'd from his High Place and Dignity, by a Bill of Excluſion: Inſomuch as it is credibly reported by ſome, that the <hi>Cat-a-moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Plebeian</hi> Creatures in the Grates, are already entred into a ſtrict <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> to caſt off their Allegiance to the Popiſh Lyon (under whom they were born) and to adhere unanimouſly to the <hi>Perkin</hi>-Lion, or Leopard, who is the Natural Son of a <hi>Lyon</hi> and a <hi>Pard.</hi> And, ſo far as he is a Creature born of two Families at once, claims to be a <hi>Lyon</hi> by the Father's ſide, as he is of the Family of the <hi>Panthers</hi> by the Mother's. Now the main Contrivance, if not the whole Manage and carrying on of this Deſign of the Beaſts Revolt from the true-born <hi>Lyon</hi> to the Baſtard <hi>Leopard,</hi> is generally laid upon the <hi>Cat,</hi> as beeing eſteem'd by all a ſubtle, ſly, ſhifting Creature, and whoſe activity in climbing is well known, no leſs than its Dexterity in ſhifting upon every Fall, ſo as in every Toſs and Revolution of Fortune, it hath been found to light upon its Feet. And albeit the Nature of the <hi>Lyon</hi> is, never to hurt, or trample upon the Proſtrate, and that he is a Creature ſo Generous in the Uſe of his Royal Power, as even under him <hi>the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> when they ſubmit, <hi>fall gently.</hi> And though none hath oftner taſted of his Princely Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or leſs deſerved it than the <hi>Cat;</hi> inſomuch, as if we number his Eſcapes from the Paw of Juſtice, he ſeems, when all Reprieves are reckon'd, to have liv'd, even beyond the Natural Term of Nine Lives: Yet all this notwithſtanding, ſo it is, that this active, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Creature, though neither in Strength nor Courage is of a ſize for bold and daring Attempts; in hunting its Prey not caring to obſerve the Laws of a free and equal Chace; but induſtriouſly waiting the Advantages of ſecret Ambuſhes, ſudden ſurprizals, and cloſe lurking in the dark: and when it is hunted hard, truſting rather to neat ſhiftings, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47322:3"/>nimble Eſcapes, than to any ſolid Reſiſtance, or open Force. Nor is it better armed by Nature for Combat, the beſt of its Weapons being no other than an envenom'd Tongue, and ſharp Fangs, ſtill impotently venting its wretched Malice in ſuch feeble Expreſſions, as Spitting and Scratching, Aſperſing and Blemiſhing all thoſe it cannot fairly run down and conquer; and for ſuch Enemies it cannot march in Combat, it ſpares not filthily to Defile, or lewdly to Disfigure them, by caſting Indecencies, and ſetting marks of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace upon them: In all Aſſaults and Encounters ſtill truſting to the baſeſt Advantages, its Tongue and its Feet; nor unjuſtly, for the Weak in Fight, are often found at once the beſt prepared for Defiance and Eſcape: Even this little, deſpicable Animal, which is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered and overmatch'd by every Creature, unleſs it may be an innocent Dove, or an harmleſs Robin, of ſo petty and inconſiderable Account, that it hath not the luck to paſs for a Mock-Lyon, or a Beaſt of Prey, but among the feeble Mice, among whom it playes the arrand Tyrant, and acts over all the Rigours of the Lyon with an ill Grace. Such is the unparallel'd Pride, and intolerable Vanity of this Ridiculous Creature, that not a ſilly Mouſe e're goes to Pot, but muſt be ſacrific'd with all the Solemnity of the Theatre, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the poor deluded Captive with a ſhew of Paſtimes and Playes, though all the mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Sport ends in this, the poor Mouſe is at length miſerably cheated out of its Life with an Interlude, A piece of Pageantry as uſeleſs as it is Barbarous, but that we may ſuppoſe the Coward Murderer turns Death and Maſſacre into Ridicule, becauſe the Death of a Mouſe is ſo terrible without this Diſguiſe, that it hath not Courage enough to kill it but in jeſt. Even this ſame Trifle of a Creature, preſuming too much on the Gallantry of the Lyon, and that he is of a Nature too Generous, and too brave to ſtoop to any thing ſo unequal in Chace or Combat, and having been too long neglected by the Lyon, in a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble kind of Scorn, vainly ſuppoſing this Diſdain to be no other than Fear, and miſtaking this Neglect for Licence, hath, from ſuch Encouragements, ſtept into ſome Point of good Opinion of himſelf, and of Reputation with other Brutes, with whom, of late, he hath proceeded to act clandeſtinely, not a little to the Diſadvantage of the Lyon. A thing the leſs to be wondred at, ſince the moſt impotent of Creatures have ever prov'd the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Underminers; and Hiſtories tell us, of a whole Town in <hi>Spain</hi> undermined by the Conies, and that the Moles, as feeble and blind as they are, did as much for another in <hi>Africk.</hi> But this Deſign againſt the King of the Beaſts, had not in likelihood arrived to this Perfection, but that the Miſchief was at firſt deſpis'd, and the Actors in it improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſlighted. Whereas, alas! things of Tragical importance have had their Riſe from very ſlender and improbable Beginnings; and Cats have ordinarily, from a very ſmall Acquaintance, with the Favour and Indulgence of their Maſters, proceeded to ſurprize them by the Throat. Moreover, no Beaſt whatſoever ſeems to be formed with greater Advantages of Nature for a Conſpirator than the Cat, as being a ſly, skulking, thieviſh Creature, and living, for the moſt part, by ſurprize and ſtealth, and whoſe courſe of Life is, in a manner, wholly led in the dark; inaſmuch as its Walks, its Watches, and its Chace, are altogether in the Night: and therefore its ſteps and motions muſt, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of neceſſity paſs undiſcern'd and undiſcovered of all, becauſe few Creatures elſe have walking Eyes, or Sight in the dark; and thoſe few that have, are near Allies to the Cat or his Game (and Thieves are not very famous for diſcovering one another) One of them being of <hi>Puſs's</hi> Family, if not of <hi>Puſs's</hi> Calling too; and the other, but that it lives more aloft, might paſs for his Prey, with a very little difference, I mean the <hi>Owl</hi> and the <hi>Bat,</hi> which are, in downright <hi>Engliſh,</hi> no other than Cat and Mouſe among the Birds. To this we may add, that what the Cat is wanting in due proportions of Strength and Courage, it evermore abundantly ſupplies in the skill of Fineneſſes, of petty Tricks, and all the little wily Arts, for which this Creature is wont to be celebrated, and in which it is arrived to ſo eminent a degree of Reputation, as even that ingenious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine which curious Art hath formed to ſupply the place of a Cat, and to do <hi>Puſs's</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his abſence, and which hath given Name to all the fine Policies which either Wit or Malice have invented, to catch Men or Beaſts; I mean the ſame which the Vulgar call a <hi>Trap,</hi> is no more than Puſs <hi>in effigie,</hi> and but a duller imitation of a Cat, in Wood.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47322:3"/>
            <p>But, to return to our purpoſe. No where hath this little <hi>Machiavel</hi> employed great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Diligence, or more conſtant Application, and upon no occaſion whatſoever ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more Addreſs, or ſet more Engines and Arts on work, than of late, againſt the Lyon, and his Royal State and Dignity. All hath been done, which the lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Wit could ſuggeſt, or the baſeſt Malice put in practice: And, in fine, nothing that lay within the lawleſs Power of ill Nature, Calumny, Ingratitude and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, hath been omitted. One while, with loud Cries, exclaiming long and largely againſt the ill Government, and Arbitrary Rule of the Lyon, though this little Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, at the ſame time, ſpares none of the leſſer Fry, that hath either Wings or Feet: Another while, with bitter Catterwawlings, bemoaning the hard Burthens, and miſerable Slavery of the Beaſts under ſuch an Oppreſſor, of whoſe Generoſity and Goodneſs Himſelf hath had but too large Experience; till, what with moving Speeches, Cajollery, and a counterfeit Zeal, working upon that Diſcontent which he hath raiſed, he proceeds to engage the unwary, unthinking Brutes, under the ſoft Name, and ſpecious Notion of Liberty, and being Aſſertors of Themſelves, and that, firſt, into Rebellion, and then into Ruine: Having, at the ſame time, drawn in the Leopard (though a By-blow of the Lyons) to be a prime Leader, and principal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of this unnatural Rebellion againſt his Father, and his Race. But this Baſe Son of the Lyon is eſteemed a pure Property of the Cat's, inſomuch as, even in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſcourſe, he ordinarily paſſes under the Name of the Cats-Foot, though, in concluſion, the poor deluded Stalking horſe meets with no other Return for his good Services, than to be fed with dazling ſhews of empty Honour, and to be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with catching at the ſhadow of Sovereignty. And accordingly, for crowning his vain hopes, great Endeavours are uſed for removing the Ducal-Lyon in the Tower (the onely one left at preſent) out of the way, as a Popiſh Sight; and for provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that in all future Solemnities of ſhewing the Lyons in the Tower, to Strangers and curious Spectators, the Leopard there be henceforth in his ſtead duely ſhewed as a Lyon. A Ceremony ſo ridiculous, as turns even the whole Conſpiracy into a Jeſt, and which raiſed no ſmall Mirth among the Graver ſort, and created no leſs laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter among ethers, than if they had ſeen, the ſecond time, the ſight of the Aſs in the Lyons Skin. Though, at the ſame time, to promote the Belief of this Impoſture, many fair ſtories are told the People, of the Lyon's Fierce and Intractable Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and of his unmerciful Uſage of All that come to ſee him, that no Den in the Tower is ſufficient to hold him, no Chain nor Law ſtrong enough to Bind him, but that he will of neceſſity break looſe, ſeize, and tear every Spectator in pieces, as his Prey. All which, and much more, is eaſily ſwallowed by the credulous Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, who take all ſhews for Realities, and receive Repreſentations for Truth, not having the Wit to diſtinguiſh betwixt their Friends and their Enemies, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than by taking it for granted, that All that ſpeak them fair are the One, as All that are ill ſpoken of are the Other; and who, in ſhort, never fail to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon, becauſe they never duely conſider, that the Lyon is not ſo fierce as he is painted.</p>
            <p>Nor is it to be imagined, how much theſe groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Belief of the Countrey People, inſomuch, that in many places, they have already proceeded ſo far, as to take down the Lyon from the King's Arms in their Churches, and from their Signs in the Countrey Towns, and to advance the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard with a Crown in the place of the Lyon in both: though, for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if it may take place, it would be convenient, for the compleat extinguiſhing and utter expunging all memory of ſo Monarchical a Creature, that the <hi>Norman</hi> Lyons in the Coin, which came in with the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> might be removed, to make way for the Leopards. But, for the above-mentioned Reformations both in City and Countrey reſpectively, ſome zealous Patrons, forſooth, are not wanting to varniſh them o're with ſpecious Pretences, and to frame, as they think, ſome colourable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes for obtruding the Leopard upon Spectators for the Lyon, in ſhewing the Lyons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47322:4"/>in the Tower; and likewiſe for advancing this new Supporter to the Kings Arms in the Countrey Churches, and ſo, upon all ſuch Loyal Signs in their Towns as the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on poſſeſſed before, uſurping no leſs boldly upon our Reaſon, with ſuch pittiful Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, than the Leopard hath already on the Lyon's Dignity. In order to this end, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fine Stories are told us, of the Beauty and Gracefulneſs of the Figure of the Leopard, of his Parentage, and of many exact reſemblances of his Father the Lyon, but much ſoftned with a milder, and more agreeable Aſpect of his own, and what fair Hopes may all conceive from ſo promiſing a Creature, as inherits at once the Majeſty and Graces of the Lyon, tempered with a more certain ſweetneſs, more peculiar to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And for Succeſſion in the Right Line, they are bold to tell us, that it matters not ſo long as the Nobler Beaſts of Prey at leaſt, whether true born or not, are all the Lyon's Couſins, and therefore of the Blood Royal; and, which is the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge they are driven to, they ſtick not to affirm, that all the Beaſts of the Field are born equal, and therefore it could be none of Natures intendment, that any One ſhould have Sovereignty or Rule over another, inaſmuch as they were all Free-born: and for that cauſe, it was not the Antient, or juſt Right of any one, like a <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or Mighty Hunter, to tyrannize over all the reſt, but that the ſame was a manifeſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment againſt Nature, and an unjuſt Uſurpation, which came in at firſt by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and Conqueſt. Now ſuch is the ill luck of thoſe that have ſtarted ſuch kind of Arguments, as it is very obſervable, that there is not one of them but may be turned with greater force on the Lyon's behalf, upon the Objectors themſelves; they being, all of them, but falſe and fading Colours, which will eaſily fall off and vaniſh, by a juſt conſideration how ill they become that Cauſe they are pretended to adorn. What is miſ-called Beauty and Mildneſs of Aſpect in the Leopard, is, in truth, when we give it the right Name, no other than a baſe and amorous Delicacy. And, inſtead of the Majeſty and Graces of the Lyon, tempered with a peculiar ſweetneſs of his own, we may rather behold the Maſculine Graces and Majeſty of the Lyon, his Father, gilt with the ſoft and wanton effeminacy of his Proſtitute Mother, the Panther, from whom he receives a ſtronger Tincture than from his Father; witneſs all his Spots, which remain as ſo many legible and laſting Stains of his Mothers Luſt and Polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and yet his Motley Skin is not a Livery unworthy the Mongrel, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his pled Anceſtors were Sire and Dam of two ſeveral Colours. Indeed, what elſe could be expected would enſue, when in ſo bold a contradiction to the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Law, Nature would go to Plow with Creatures more unequally yoaked than an Oxe and an Aſs? For the ſame unevenneſs and incongruity appears evermore in Nature's miſ-matching of Creatures, which is daily found in Art's mis-match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Metals, where the purer and more refined Metal is really much embaſed and impoveriſh'd by its mixture with a courſer, and yet, at the ſame time, the courſer Metal it ſelf rendred much more courſe, by appearing in Conjunction with a Finer. Nor fares it otherwiſe in the preſent caſe; that Majeſty which ſhines pure and bright in the Lyon, when ſtamped on the Leopard, looks dim, and is clouded, as being embaſed with the courſe Allay of the Panther; where, inſtead of the Pard's being dignified by Riſing into Lyon, the Lyon is rather wholly degraded, by degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting altogether into Pard. What ſhall we ſay more to the Boaſt of the Leopard's Parentage and Extraction? Why ſure that they were at a loſs to make a Boaſt of that which is ſo ſoul a ſhame and diſparagement; and is ſo far from being of the Nature of a Plea, that it is indeed no other than an Imputation. For, either they ought to have concealed that part of the Truth which they are not aſhamed to publiſh or elſe, not to have concealed the other part which they are aſhamed to publiſh; and not to have made ſuch a noiſe of his Father, as, at the ſame time, quite drowns all Report and Speech of his Mother. For, what though he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the King of Beaſts, yet ſtill was it not by his Queen, but on the proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Body of a baſe Subject. And, if ſuch promiſcuous and vile Engendring was no ſmall Diminution of Honour to the Royal Sire, ſure then it cannot be urged as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47322:4"/>the leaſt Acceſſion of Honour to his Baſtard Iſſue. Be it granted, that he had a Royal Father, yet this in no wiſe intitles him to the Name, and Priviledge of a Royal Son, being indeed but a Leap by chance, and no more than a Creature of Fortune. For, whereas nothing can get a Lyon but a Lyon, the Leopard quite otherwiſe, though he may have the King of Beaſts for his Father, muſt ſtand to the courteſie of the whole Herd for a Mother. The next Plea drawn from thoſe exact Reſemblances of his Royal Sire, which are to be found in his Spurious Iſſue, is ſo frivolous, as rather merits a Smile for its Confutation, than a ſerious Anſwer. For, who could expect that ſhould be turned to his Praiſe, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but matter of Sport? For, let ſuch tell me, if, at leaſt, they can, be ſerious, is it any part of the Ape's Praiſe, that, in the firſt forming him, he began to be made Man, but was left off before he was finiſhed; for which reaſon, the poor chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Creature is diſowned by the Herd, as being but an Eſſay of a Brute, and imperfectly Theirs; and yet, at the ſame time, diſdained by men, as being no more than dough-bak'd, and unfiniſh'd Man. In like manner, who can imagine otherwiſe, but that the Leopard, when he was made, would fain have been a Lyon if he durſt. And accordingly he ventur'd a little way, and made ſome few faint ſteps towards it, but, in concluſion, his Courage failing him, he was wrought off in haſte, as you ſee, before the moiſt-ſtrokes were perfected. And now, I beſeech you, behold the profound Argument. The Leopard is the very picture of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What then? Therefore let's fairly rid City and Country at once of the true Original. Admirably urged, but that ſuch an Inference hath no more the true Force and Colour of right Reaſon, than the Leopard hath of the Majeſtick ſhew and ſtrength of the Lyon's true-born Iſſue. No, rather, let us love the Original and the Copy preſented together in one view, that ſo, from a cloſe and near Survey of Both at once, we may come up to all the Meaſures of an equal and juſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. But theſe men, who are ſo fond of beholding the Picture of a Lyon, and, at the ſame time, will needs appear ſo eager for baniſhing the Original, I doubt not may have learn'd ſo neceſſary a Policy from, <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s Painter, who, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a wretched Figure of a Cock, and publickly expoſed the ſame, though poſſibly; even ſo ill a Picture might have paſſed for a good Malkin or Scare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crow, had yet, notwithſtanding, employed his Boy on purpoſe to chaſe away all the Cocks and Hens in the Yard, from appearing to the juſt Reproach and Scandal of ſo lewd a piece of Painting; as well knowing, that even the faireſt Counterfeits are evermore ſeen with the greateſt Advantages, when the Truth is not in view, and that all wants and weakneſſes in the Imitations of Art, never have the luck to be ſo eaſily betrayed, as when they are compar'd near at hand, with the Life. Now, is the wiſe Contrivance of theſe men any other than the very Moral of this Story? and have they not adventured to eſtabliſh the precarious Reputation of the Leopard, by the ſelf-ſame Means and Methods, which their Maſter, the unhappy Painter, had made choice of, as the likelieſt, to make the beſt of a bad Market? For what elſe mean the repeated Propoſals and endeavours ſtill on foot, for diſpoſſeſſing the Lyon of that place he hath long held in the Tower, and of obtruding the Leopard for a Lyon upon all Spectators? And what elſe ſignifie the like unwearied Attempts, of cozening the credulous Countrey People with a Leopard for a Lyon, in the Kings Arms, and ſo many of their Sign-Poſts in the Countrey Towns? Do they not plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to all by ſuch a wretched ſhift, how unwilling they are that the enormous Diſproportion and Diſparity between the Lyon's Genuine Iſſue and his Baſtard, ſhould be betrayed, upon a near and juſt compariſon of both together? For then, as they are conſcious to themſelves, that Generous Vigour, that Heroick Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and thoſe Maſculine Graces which eminently ſhine in their full Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſit on the Majeſtick Fore-head of the One, will all appear as undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the weak Approaches to, and faint Emulations of all theſe will in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47322:5"/>Other, which is the baſe and inglorious Counterfeit: whereas, they are pleaſed to ſay, that for Succeſſion in the Right Line, it matters not, it is barely ſaid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any colour of Proof, and is ſo ſlender a Cavil, as carries with it, it's own Confutation; Succeſſion and Birth-right being no other than the plain and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Courſe and Order of Nature: which Order is no ſooner broke at any time, but all things, by an immediate Conſequence, fall into direct Confuſion, no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination being left of Firſt and Laſt, no Diſtinction of Leaders and Led; and in fine, no Eſtabliſhment of Right and Wrong, all things being reſolved into the Power of blind Fortune, and committed to the unſteady Determinations of giddy Chance: Nor is it to be repreſented in any Senſe, but the diſorderly Face of an Army, fencing with it ſelf, and put to Rout by it's own Forces; or to be march'd with any Inſtance, but the wild Encounters in the Air, of ravenous <hi>Kites</hi> and <hi>Crows,</hi> rudely flocking and fighting together, as preying on one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without Diſtinction, Method, or Meaſure. Nor does that which follows, mend the matter, when they add, that the nobler Beaſts of Prey at leaſt, whether true born or not, are all the Lyon's Cozens; as, if in caſe the Lyon were diſabled, yet the Succeſſion need not be loſt. But, alas! What can be more vain than ſuch Diſcourſes? Since, upon the Remove of the Succeſſion, the whole Fabrick tumbles down, and the very Situation and Figure of the Government, are at once entirely deſtroyed; for, the Right of governing being once loſt, who is there under the Right of being governed? And where no one is under any Right of being governed, there all have equally a Right to govern: and thus, in Concluſion, the Government is unavoidably toſt, like a Ball of Contention, from one to another, among as many Pretenders, as there are Members of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and a Gap is open for a Civil War, in every Age; ſo impoſſible is it, even for the Monarchy it ſelf, any where to out-live the Succeſſion, unleſs any think it practicable, for the Monarchy to laſt, when the Foundations are gone; which Foundations, are no ſooner removed, but the many ſhort-liv'd Viciſſitudes und Revolutions of State, which happen to ſtart up on a ſudden, in it's ſtead, (like haſty Muſhrooms, which are but the Birth of a Night) will appear no other than the May-games of Chance, and mere Sportings of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; by all which reſtleſs Throws, and innumerable Toſſes and Turnings from ſide to ſide, Nature ſeems abundantly to declare, That ſhe is ill at Eaſe, and can never poſſibly be at reſt, till ſuch time, as all things whatever out of frame and place, duely recover their right Center, and return to ſettle on the ancient Bottom. But, theſe zealous Aſſertors of the Pretenſions and Claims of all the nobler Beaſts, at leaſt, as the Lion's Cozens, and therefore, of the Blood Royal, have committed ſure, no ſmall Overſight, in neglecting, when ſo fair Occaſion offered, to garniſh this Point, with many fine Stories of <hi>Alexander's Bucephalus,</hi> and how <hi>Caligula</hi> did his Horſe the Honour, to make him a Conſul, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, he was no more unworthy the Conſulſhip, than his Maſter the Empire: then they might have proceeded farther, That the two Brothers that laid the firſt Foundation of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Greatneſs, <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Rhemus,</hi> were not aſhamed to owe the Charge and Nurſery of their tender Years, to the kindneſs of a Wolf. From theſe old Stories, they might have led us yet, to more modern Inſtances, and acquainted us, that of late the Landtgrave of <hi>Heſſe</hi> hath declared himſelf ſo far in Favour of the <hi>Cat,</hi> as he now gives that Creature in his Arms, and even at this day, glories in no other Stile, than that of Prince of the <hi>Cats.</hi> To paſs b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of <hi>Whittington</hi>'s Cat, ſo celebrated in Stories of our own; and what? Even the <hi>Turkiſh Aleoran,</hi> if that at leaſt affords us any authentick Records of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, hath left us no other Original of the <hi>Cat,</hi> but this, That the King of Beaſts ſneezing, was delivered of a Cat at his Noſtrils; whether that Cuſtom hence took Riſe or no, I know not, ſo much in ordinary uſe yet among the Common People, of ſaluting this Creature upon occaſion, by the Name of <hi>Puſs, in her Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47322:5"/>
            <p>But what needs all this adoe? Will ſome ſay, when the Argument which they retreat to as their laſt Refuge, when all the reſt fail, flatly aſſures us, That all the Beaſts are equal, and that Nature having left us no exact ſcale of Creatures, it could be none of her Intendment, that any one ſhould have Rule or Sovereignty more than another; the Truth of which bold Aſſertion, is daily confronted by every Obſervation: the Fowls of the Air being no more equal either in point of Sharpneſs of Sight, Strength of Talons, or their towring Flight, than the Trees in which they build, are found aſpiring to an Equality in Pitch and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence: nor is there more a Parity among the Beaſts of the Field, in regard of their Proweſs, Strength of Body, or natural Weapons, than the Earth on which they couch, is every where, all of a level; part of which, is ſeen ever and anon; proudly aſcending to be crown'd with lofty Hills, while part bows down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and ſtoops ſo low, till it ſubmits it ſelf into humble Vallies. Nay, to avoid the Conſuſion of Equality, even in ſo much as the mingling ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors as Water and Oyl, it is obſerved, that Oyl, as affecting the ſupreme Place, will evermore be getting uppermoſt, and keeping the Water in Subjection, to be ſure to float a top: much more, among all Orders and Ranks of Creatures, hath it been the conſtant rule and unalterable Appointment of Nature, to ſelect ſome one from the reſt of the Flocks and Herds, whom ſhe hath accordingly formed with peculiar Graces, and crown'd with nobler Prerogatives, and every way eminently ſignalized with greater Advantages, as it ſhould ſeem on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; that where thoſe fair Marks of natural Authority and Majeſty, ſhine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, they might appear to all, worthily preferred to be the Chief and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the furr'd or feather'd Kind: to ſay then, that all the Birds of the Air, or Beaſts of the Forreſt, are equal, is ſuch another Soleciſm in effect, as to affirm, that all the Birds are Eagles, or that all the Beaſts are Lyons.</p>
            <p>To proceed then, whoever ſhall conſider that innate Dread and Reverence, which common Inſtinct hath implanted in all Beaſts of their King, and which he duely ſeems to challenge from them, as their natural Homage and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as often as he roars, or laſhes the Ground with his incenſed Tail, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall reflect on his own mere Generoſity and Gallantry, in ſpaving to inſult upon the Proſtrate, as well as on his invincible and matchleſs Courage, in admitting no Equal, and enduring no Superiour, either in Chace or Combat: In a Word, whoever ſhall follow that Painters Example, who computed the Proportions, and took the Meaſures of an entire Lyon, by ſeeing no more than his Foot; and ſhall in like manner, proceed to a true Eſtimate of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Majeſty of this royal Creature, from ſo ſmall a Hint, as that little Image or Signature of a Crown, which Nature hath viſibly ſtamped in his Imperial Paw: I ſay, he that deliberately weighs any or all of theſe, will, in the end, upon the whole matter, conclude, that the Lyon's Rights are no more to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, than himſelf; and that as no Creature whatever is the Lyon's juſt Match in a fair Field, ſo alſo, no Arguments againſt his Claims and Pretenſions to a natural Empire and Dominion over the Beaſts, as his Inheritance, will be ſound of equal Force and Strength to thoſe for them. Nor does he hold his Reign by ſuch a Tenure as came in with the Conquerour, this Rule being an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of ſuch Antiquity, as is beyond the Memory of many Ages, and of which, neither the eldeſt men nor Records, can aſſign the firſt Beginning; and certainly, ſuch a Rule as this, of which we can trace no Beginning, could have no other, than purely from God and Nature; for, were it true that it was no better than an Uſurpation, which came in by Myſtery and Conqueſt, as hath been ſuggeſted: it might ſtill deſerve a Queſtion, whether or no, in thoſe Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Uſurpation, there were not Lyons, as well as in all Ages ſince? And if ſo, whether the Lyons of former Ages were e're a jot tamer, or leſs Lyons than thoſe of later Ages? and then, at length, when they came to uſurp, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47322:6"/>get all the Power into their Clutches, what Ages it firſt came in, the who, or what Creature living it was that they uſurped upon? For, but now we were told, that before ſuch time, as this Uſurpation took place, all Creatures were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual; and, it is plain, that among Equals, no one hath a Right of Maſtery over another, and where there was no Right, there could indeed be no Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if this Imperial Right came in at firſt by Maſtery and Conqueſt, ſince every Conqueſt is but the Fortune of the War, and nothing can be more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant than the Succeſſes of Fortune, it may be demanded farther, how it hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that the King of Beaſts hath been crowned with conſtant Succeſſes againſt every Creature, in all Diſputes for the Maſtery? and no Creature, with any Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, againſt him? And, whence comes it to paſs, that this <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or Mighty Hunter, hath been never, at any time, Himſelf hunted out of his Rights, run down upon the Spot, and fairly killed by none of the baſer Herd? If it be ſaid here, that the Royal Creature is ſo far ſuperiour to the reſt in Strength and Spirit, that he ſeems to be formed with greater Advantages than all others for a Natural Conqueſt; ſuch an Anſwer will ſtill leave room for a farther En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry; why Nature, who is ſuppoſed to do nothing in vain, ſhould be ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral of her Favours to no end and purpoſe? and, whether it be reaſonable to imagine, that ſhe ſhould Arm any Creature whatſoever, for a Natural Conqueſt, unleſs ſhe had deſigned the ſame for Natural Monarchy.</p>
            <p>And thus, at length, I have diſpatched the ſeveral Arguments produced for ſetting up the Leopard in the room of the Lyon's True-born Iſſue, all of which, as you may obſerve, but the laſt, plead for a new King of Beaſts, as that in the end for no King of Beaſts. So nearly are the Succeſſion and the Monarchy allied, that the change of the Succeſſion, is by one and the ſame Fate, both in the Practice and Propoſal of the King, evermore made a ſtep to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. For, as all the preceding Arguments are framed to diſable the Lyon's next Heir from inheriting his Imperial Rights, ſo the laſt is framed no leſs to diſable the Baſtard Pretender, or any other. But, I hope, by what hath been ſaid, it will ſufficiently appear, that the Lyon and a juſt Cauſe are both alike ſtrong and invincible, and not to be diſabled by any Force whatſoever.</p>
            <p>One thing I had almoſt forgot to note, that whereas there were ſome Propoſals of ſhewing the Leopard and the Cat more publickly in Remoter parts of the Countrey, accordingly, of late, ſome Progreſſes have been made in that matter, and not without ſome ſmall Succeſs, as it was not otherwiſe likely. For, upon their firſt Approach, ſome ſilly Brutes in the Countrey, that had never ſeen the Tower, nor the Lyons in their Lives, through a well-meaning and miſ-taught Ignorance, paid their miſtaken Reverence to the Leopard, as to the King of Beaſts. Upon which occaſion, it is incredible to imagine, how ſtrangely his little Oracle, the Cat, is tranſported, as little Creatures are evermore the vaineſt; witneſs the Fly in <hi>Aeſop,</hi> which was in great trouble forſooth, for the mighty Duſt it raiſed, that, in truth, was ſtirred by the motion of the Chariot-wheel, on the top of which it perch'd: but alas, good Soul! his Cat-ſhip ſeems to be fallen into the ſame miſtake with the Aſs in the Story, that carried the Image of <hi>Iſis,</hi> which fondly imagined, as this profound Creature was no wiſer, that all the Honours were paid to him, which were indeed directed to the Image of the Goddeſs: And thus, in like manner, the Caps and Cringings of the Countrey Clowns, which the Cat hath, with no little Vanity, arrogated to himſelf and the Leopard, were purely addreſſed to the fair Image of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> which was publickly expoſed, and carried before them; and the ſame might be poſſibly increaſed in ſome places, by the roaring Noiſes they made againſt Popery where-ever they came. So that, upon a right underſtanding, I do not ſee that the Cat is in great danger of being had in Idolatry, though Time was, they ſay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47322:6"/>when Sacrifices and Altars to the Race of <hi>Tybert</hi> and <hi>Grimalkin</hi> were in faſhion. And, if this will gratifie any of the Nine-liv'd Immortal Kind, it ſhall be freely acknowledged, that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> made no ſcruple to admit this Creature in the number of their Gods; and, accordingly, <hi>Puſs</hi> was, with great Formality, ſhut up in her Temple, and kept to be ſhew'd in State, with a falſe, diſſembling <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile,</hi> and ſuch like good company; though it ought to be impartially reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mbred withal, that theſe good People, who were ſo Devout as to worſhip a Cat, were led, as we may ſuppoſe, with the ſame blindneſs or Zeal, to acknowledge, no leſs worthily, even Darkneſs it ſelf for a Deity.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay more ? To lay before you all, the Fineneſſes and thin-ſpun Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of our little <hi>Machiavil,</hi> were an attempt, not unlike that of <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> who had with great Care, cauſed all the Cobwebs in <hi>Rome,</hi> to be brought and laid together in a place; that all the curious Labors of thoſe little venemous Creatures, being amaſſed together in one Heap, and preſented in one View, all might from thence proceed to compute the Greatneſs of <hi>Rome,</hi> and take their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Extent of its Buildings, which could conveniently Lodge ſo vaſt a Number of Spiders at once; though ſuch a Choice Collection of their Webbs, might be expoſed with better reaſon, for a Map of the Sluttiſhneſs of <hi>Rome,</hi> than for any Tipe of its Greatneſs.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this way of Calculation might prove very fallacious: For perhaps, there was hardly any naſty, little Village, but might have afforded a more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Harveſt of Cobwebs, than the Imperial City it ſelf.</p>
            <p>However, ſuch it ſeems were the worthy Employments of the Emperors in thoſe days: For as one very induſtriouſly applied himſelf to that Imperial Sport in Hunting Flies, another was very gravely taken up, in ſo laudable an Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, as the ſweeping of Cobwebs together, and crowding them up in an Heap.</p>
            <p>In this State are things depending at preſent, what the Iſſue and Event of all may be, as yet is not a little uncertain: In the mean time, Conjectures are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and Cenſures are ſpent, with ſuch Variety of Difference, as men ſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly affected. One Party are of Opinion, that it ſhews but little Skill, to rowſe a Sleeping Lyon: And that it is no leſs, than a point of intolerable Vanity, to reckon upon the Lyon's Skin. and proceed to ſhare the Spoil ſo long before he be caught. Another Party, which makes no great Noiſe for its Zeal to Monarchy, and cannot over-paſſionately wiſh it a long Continuance, either among Men or Beaſts, ſeem to take the ſame malicious Pleaſure in fore-ſeeing its Ruine, which ſome do, in looking on a Shipwrack, and accordingly, live but only in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch brisk Steps and hopeful Beginnings, being proportionably improved, and fairly carried on, propoſing, by Change of Governors, to change their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and Conditions.</p>
            <p>But theſe vain Hopes are as much derided, by a third ſort of Men, who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, ever and anon, that Lands, and Servants, and Fortunes, have evermore the beſt Uſage under their Old Maſters; and are ſure to be the moſt gently treated by their Right Owners: Whereas Uſurpers, who are the greateſt Robbers in the World, for the moſt part, lead ſuch a merry, jovial Courſe of Life, as Thieves uſe to do, idly ſquandring, and notoriouſly waſting, what in Concluſion is none of their own.</p>
            <p>What remains then, but that it ſhould fare with other Creatures, in ſuch Variety of Changes, much as it did with the <hi>Frogs</hi> in the Fable, who could not away with the Gentleneſs of an eaſy <hi>Log;</hi> and therefore, were deſervedly preyed upon in the end, by a devouring <hi>Stork.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, when Governments are once ſo miſerable, as to be in the Hands of the baſer Herd, they ſeem to diſpoſe of them as wildly as Boys of their Cocks, which they ſet up, only for the fond ſport of knocking them down again.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47322:7"/>
            <p>There are in Concluſion, to add no more, who are of belief, that the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Succeſs of this Impoſure, is not altogether owing ſo much to the Manage of ſome, as to the Inadvertency of others, with whom, every fair Tale paſſes for Truth, that hath the Fortune to be well told; and whatever hath the luck to make a good Figure, or a fine Shew at a diſtance, is taken for no leſs than it ſeems: For this Miſchief had never been fomented, and fed to ſuch a Degree; but that the well-meaning Brutes, have been leſs diligent and daring, leſs circumſpect and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous, than the crafty Cat, and his cloſe Confederates, whoſe familiar Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is haunting of blind Corners, obſcure Places and Holes; and lying, ever and anon upon the Catch, to ſurpriſe the unwary: It being the conſtant, unhappy Lot of ſuch Creatures as are innocent, not ſuſpecting themſelves, and their own Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to be leſs apprehenſive and ſuſpitious than they ought, of the pernicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and ill Practices of others; and for that reaſon, to lie more open, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the ſecret Arts and Endeavors of their Enemies: Nay, what is more, even among ſuch as could ſee farther, and had a clearer Proſpect before them; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one neglecting all Care and Thought of the Common Danger, ſeems to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide no farther than for his own Security, untill, in the end, it happen to them, as to men in a Storm, where, while every one caſts about, to ſave no more than one, all the Paſſengers drown together.</p>
            <p>And thus in the Caſe before us, as to the Attempt of hanging the Bell about the Cat's Neck, every one declines, and ſhifts off ſo neceſſary a Service from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to another, till at length, what no one durſt adventure upon, is left un-at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by all. Whereas, alas! this growing Miſchief, which hath ſo fatally prevailed and ſpread, ſince the Cat was under reſtraint in the Tower, might have been ſeaſonably prevented and ſtop'd at firſt, by a timely Riddance of the Cat out of the way. A Courſe which had been no leſs neceſſary for the Common Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than that applauded Cuſtom, yet of frequent uſe, in times of General Sickneſs and Contagion; when, among other means to divert the ſpreading of the Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the People turn Executioners, and with their own Hands, fail not to do So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Juſtice on all the Cats in the Town.</p>
            <p>I may be thought perhaps, by ſome, to have introduc'd Brute Creatures upon the Stage, deſigning and acting beyond their Powers and Capacities; and ſo to have taken a Liberty, beyond even the Extravagance of Romances: For though they are allowed to be ſuch Pictures as ſhew us things much bigger than the Life; and that their Giants are much larger than thoſe in any Age; their Horſes fairer than thoſe bred in any Country; their Armor brighter than what is at any time made in the Shops; and their Shipping fairer, than any the Univerſal World af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords: Yet notwithſtanding, it may deſerve a Queſtion,</p>
            <p>Whether their Brutes are ſo artificial and ingenious, ſo well bred and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd, as to lay Plots and form Deſigns, or at leaſt, to be ſo far concern'd in Man's witty way of Rebellion, as to enter into Cabals, or engage in Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Clubs?</p>
            <p>But then ſuch as ſtart theſe Scruples, may pleaſe to remember, that there are Thoughtful Beaſts, as well as there are Unthinking Men in the World; and that the Odds is not ſo great betwixt the Plodding Carrier and his Pack horſe; but that it may come to a Queſtion, which is the Carrier, and which the Beaſt? Such Men as have the conſtant Charge and Attendance of Beaſts, being indeed rather Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Men, than Men themſelves, as having no more Humanity left in them, than what is ſunk to a baſe Degeneracy, and runs ſo low, as it appears at Ebb: whereas, on the contrary, ſuch Creatures as arc preferred before the reſt of the Herd, to aſſociate with man, as their Companion, or wait on him, as their Maſter, to be Partners with him in his Labor, or to ſhare with him in his Sports, are, I know not how civillz'd and improv'd, to that Degree, as they ſeem rais'd above the Common Pitch and Stature of Beaſts; and riſing very near to the height of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47322:7"/>Man, who, in the Philoſopher's Language, is no more than a <hi>Sociable Creature.</hi> The Priviledge of which Definition is by none denied to the Dog and the Horſe, as being upon every occaſion, a part of his Train, and of a piece with his Houſhold and Family, and no leſs indeed than his ordinary Menial Servants. And, for the Cat, beſides its juſt Pretenſions to the ſame Intereſts with theſe, I ſhall more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly add, that the ingenious <hi>Montaigne.</hi> playing with his Cat, found it ſo good Company, and ſuch pleaſant Entertainment, and agreeable Converſation, that he could not forbear celebrating his purring Play-fellow to all Poſterity; and purely, for Puſs's ſake, to exalt all Brute Creatures to ſome degrees of Reaſon. An Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which, it may be, he the rather inclin'd to embrace, as thinking for Mankind to damn all other Creatures whatever, as <hi>Irrational,</hi> at one Blow, was ſo hard a Cenſure, as taſted ſomewhat of that ſevere and uncharitable Pride, which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> were accuſed of, when they thought fit to Reprobate all the reſt of Mankind, beſides themſelves, as <hi>Barbarous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be true, as ſome have conſtantly affirmed, upon what grounds they beſt know themſelves, that all men whatever are found naturally to repreſent in ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, ſome one Creature or other; I hope it will not appear ſo unpardonable an Errour, and ſo far removed from that Latitude which is allowed to Fiction and Romance, to introduce Brute Creatures perſonating, and playing the parts of men; ſince, at the ſame time, Nature it ſelf, in our Compoſition, hath bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed ſo many ſtrokes and lineaments, as gives us no inconſiderable Tincture and ſemblance of ſome or other of the Brutes. Nay, even that Erection of Figure which is contended for as peculiar to Man, and, almoſt his ſole Diſcrimination from other Creatures, is not, it may be, altogether ſo natural as is imagined, when we conſider the many ſteps and Eſſays which Children make at their firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to go, to march upon all four; inſomuch as Nurſes and Leading-ſtrings, and little Chariots, are all but little enough to reclaim and reſcue them from ſuch a Motion, and which, crawling Age, of its own accord, at length returns to, in ſpite of all the vain Endeavours and ſupport of a ſtick.</p>
            <p>For the Beaſts I have made choice of for theſe Characters, I was not far to ſeek for them: The Lyon, Leopard, Cat-a-mountain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being, though not Natives of this Iſland, and born within the four Seas, yet Inhabitants within the Precincts and Liberties of the Tower, and ſo ſeem to be naturalized, and, in a, ſort, Free of the City, which is the Scene where the Story is principally laid. And then the Cat, in Right of <hi>Whittington</hi>'s <hi>Puſs,</hi> that was <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> may fairly pretend to no ſmall Intereſt in the Charter and Freedom of the City. To which, give me leave to add, that I thought the Cat no leſs fit to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain the Politick Character than the Fox, the very mention of which, is now, in a manner, nauſeous, ſince he is made to ſerve the turn ſo often in <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that he is worn all out as thread bare, as the Knight that is to get the better of the Gyant in <hi>Romances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the League between the Leopard and the Cat, and ſo between thoſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed under their Names and Characters, it is not a little countenanc'd by thoſe Alliances which Nature hath made between both theſe Creatures, in their Make, manner of Hunting, and way of Defiance: The Leopard being mark'd in Head, Feet, and Tail, like a Cat, is obſerved to ſpit as a Cat does, and, in fine, to jump upon his Prey after the ſelf-ſame manner.</p>
            <p>There needs no great Force to bring ſo near Allies, as the Leopard, Cat, and Cat-a-mountain, which the whole Faction engaged againſt the Lyon, within the Compaſs of an Aſſociation: Nature it ſelf having proceeded a little way, and made ſome ſteps towards it, in incorporating them already in ſome ſort, into a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47322:8"/>Tribe; theſe Creatures being all of them of Cat-kind, and differing at length, from a Cat, no otherwiſe than a Kite does from an Eagle.</p>
            <p>And, might it not be conveniently enough ſuppoſed, that ſuch as already were the Cat's Allies in Nature, might prove his Confederates and Accomplycies in Deſign; and as they were Creatures of his kind, turn alſo Creatures of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and accordingly (as great Bodies are moved by ſlender Springs) be pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly influenc'd, and perfectly manag'd by him, in a joint Conſpiracy againſt the King of Beaſts; he being beſides, as little Creatures ordinarily are, of a nimbler Wit, and of a finer Senſe, and having much a deeper Reach, than any of the whole Gang beſides. And though the Leopard is ſometimes ſaid to be the Leader of the Faction aganiſt the Lyon, yet is he at the ſame time alſo, called the Cat's Foot, as being indeed no more than the Handle of the Cauſe, and a Creature ſo purely paſſive, that though for Honour ſake, he hath the Name of Leader of the Faction, yet in effect, is he led by the whole Faction round, by Turns; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this empty Feather in his Cap, as the Fore-horſe in the Team; and though like him too, he ſeems to lead the Van, yet is he no leſs thruſt on, and puſh'd forwards by thoſe in the Rear. If any yet ſtubbornly inſiſt, that the Leopard is a wild Creature, and wild Creatures uſe not to appear in Herds, and therefore the Suppoſition of his affecting Cabals and Aſſociations, and Clubs, is no leſs than monſtrous, and ſuch as perfectly exceeds at once, all Imagination and Belief.</p>
            <p>To what hath been already ſaid, I ſhall add yet farther, that his very Original and Generation are ſuch, as gives Colour of Countenance to ſuch a Suppoſition, inaſmuch as he owes his Birth to an unclean Club of a Lyon and Panther, and ſo indeed, was purely begotten by an Aſſociation of two ſeveral Tribes and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. However, if I have yet made him amends, and done him as much Right another way, by ſuppoſing him as ignorant, as lame, and as much a Stranger to Buſineſs, as I found him, he being ſo errant a Property, that the only uſe which hath been made of him all along, hath been no other, than the ſhewing this pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Booby in all places, for a Sight, remaining yet, notwithſtanding a great Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Opportunities, a raw and unpracticed Novice, and no more improved, with all the Aſſiduities and Application of the Cat, than the Aſſe, in the Story, was edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that went to hear <hi>Porphyrie</hi>'s Lectures.</p>
            <p>Neither ought it to ſeem ſtrange, in the leaſt, to hear of the Cat's going a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balling, and running to Clubs, and haunting Aſſociations; for, it is no new thing, for the Cat of the Houſe, both on the Account of Catterwauling, and other Scores, to goſſip with his Comrades, and to have frequent Meetings with the Cats in the Vicinage; ſo that this is no more in Concluſion, than Cat after kind.</p>
            <p>But, becauſe the Cat is introduced as the Principal Actor in this Romance, and upon whom, in a manner, the whole Affair turns and moves, and becauſe alſo it may appear ſomewhat new for the Cat to play the part of ſuch a little Politician as it is deſigned to represent; to obviate therefore ſuch Inconvenience, I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſome Reaſons, why he may not appear altogether unworthy the Character aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd him, which ſhall be ſuch as lye open to every Conſideration, and with theſe I ſhall ſhut up the whole Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>It is a Creature of the greateſt Thought and Reflection, and evermore ſo intent upon its Sport and Prey, as its buſie imagination figures to it ſelf Rats and Mice, where-ever there are Chairs and Hangings, ſharpening and whetting its Claws perpetually againſt them, in Meditation and Conceit, perhaps, of the next Rat it is to encounter.</p>
            <p>It is a Creature ſo very Watchful and Wary, that it is ſeldome obſerved to be overtaken, and when it is, is ſo dextrous and nimble in ſhiftings and Tergiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, that, as if it were all Feet, which way ſoever it happens to be thrown,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47322:8"/>by a notable Felicity, it ſtill falls upon all four; that as <hi>Pauſo</hi>'s Horſe, which, at firſt ſight paſſed for the Picture of a Horſe o'rethrown, but, turn'd the other way, for that of a running Horſe; ſo, when upon every Toſs we look to find this Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture laid flat on his back, he, quite contrary, deceives our Expectation, and eludes the Fall at once, by lighting, unhurt, on his Feet. So far is it exempt from thoſe Miſchances to which other Creatures are ſubject, as it ſeems, in ſome degree, placed out of the Reach and Power of Deſtiny, and, in a manner, to be inchanted, for which cauſe, the waggiſh Vulgar, ſomewhat not unpleaſantly, are wont to aſcribe to it a little kind of Immortality, laſting the length of Nine Lives. And not without reaſon, when we conſider how often it hath been near the Point, and how narrowly ſtill it hath eſcaped, what a number of Forfeitures of its own Life it hath out-lived, and what a variety of Tragical Ends of others it hath out-laſted, ſo as where other Creatures have not fail'd ducly to go to pot, this hath been ever ſure to ſave his Bacon.</p>
            <p>Once for all; It is a Creature of no very fair Reputation, and under ſomewhat ſuſpitious Circumſtances, lying ſo far under the deep diſpleaſure of ſome, that nothing affords them matter of higher diſtaſte, or can be more their peculiar Averſion, or perfect abhorrence. A thing the more to be taken notice of, becauſe ſo peaceable is Nature, as ſhe evermore very ſparingly kindles theſe kinds of Feuds and Antipathies; inſomuch as in the whole number of Beaſts, that are not meer Vermine, or Venemous Creatures, there is hardly any one to be named, with whom any part of Mankind is fallen out ſo implacably, and to that degree, as to live in perpetual War and Enmity with all beſides the Cat, and which is to be treated as an Enemy to their Nature and Conſtitution, and to be baniſhed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, at the greateſt Diſtances, never to be ſeen ſo much as in their Company, or to come within the reach of their Sight or Smell. Nor ſcapes this Creature any better among the common ſort of People, with whom it is generally ſo ill in Eſteem, as it is familiar and frequent for them to reprobate all Cats for Witches; A great Indignity and ſevere Imputation for all to ſuffer under without Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but ſuch, it may be, as will ſtick more eaſily on the Cat of the Romance, if we conſider the Truth of that ſaying, that <hi>Rebellion is as the Sin of Witchcraft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I hope, however will be granted for the Honour of this little, great Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary, and, as no leſs than a due to his <hi>Catilineſhip,</hi> that the Exemplary Vertue of Rebellion, in which he hath happily excelled the moſt inimitable Maſters of his time, can never be celebrated in our Age, or recommended to Poſterity in a more advantageous and agreeable Style, than that Name it hath ſo long worthily enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of that luſty <hi>Puſs,</hi> the <hi>GOOD OLD CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
